Guide to the Press photographs of Hartford, Connecticut Black Caucus protests and meetings, 1967 September-October RL.11878
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Press photographs of Hartford, Connecticut Black Caucus protests and meetings
1967 September-October
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Chindmark, Einar G., 1912-1974
Pugliese, S. Robert, 1932-2016
Grogan, Grover W., 1926-1992
Kington, Ellery G., 1918-1984
RL.11878
0.5 Linear Feet 1 box 50 photographic prints Print sizes: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches; image sizes vary.
The Hartford Times was a daily newspaper for Hartford, Connecticut. Collection consists of 50 black-and-white press photographs taken by Hartford Times staff of Black Caucus protests and marches in Fall 1967, and associated community meetings. Subjects include Black Caucus members, African American residents, student protesters, state and city officials, police, religious leaders, and the press. Protest images show Black Caucus members marching through Hartford and gathering in the State Capitol Building and in Bushnell Park. Individuals highlighted in the images are: John Barber; Boce W. Barlow, Jr.; Rev. Collin Bennett; Lewis Fox; George B. Kinsella; Rev. Robert A. Moody; Robert Morris; and Wilber Smith. Acquired as part of the John Hope Center for African and African American History and Culture, and the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Arrangement
Photographs are arranged in chronological order.
Historical Note
The Hartford Times was the daily afternoon newspaper for Hartford, Connecticut. Its photographers assigned to cover the Black Caucus marches were Einar G. Chindmark, Grover W. Grogan, Ellery G. Kington, and S. Robert Pugliese.
The Black Caucus of Hartford was formed sometime in the first half of 1967 by residents of the North End, a segregated neighborhood where most of the African Americans in Hartford lived, and where they faced systemic discriminatory practices, including substandard housing and education, and police harassment. By 1970 the group seems to have disbanded, but individuals continued their civil rights work with other community groups and organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Press photographs of Hartford, Connecticut Black Caucus protests and meetings were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2020.
Content Description
Collection consists of 50 black-and-white press photographs taken by Hartford Times reporters of Black Caucus protests in Hartford, Connecticut in September and October, 1967, and associated community meetings. Individuals featured in the images include Black Caucus members, African American citizens of the North End, other Black and White activists, student protesters, state and city officials, police, religious leaders, and the press.
About a quarter of the prints are of protest images, and show Black Caucus leaders and members marching peacefully through Hartford and gathering in the State Capitol Building and in Bushnell Park with college student supporters. Images of meetings show speakers as well as the audiences.
Among the individuals highlighted in the images are: John Barber, Black Caucus spokesperson; Boce Barlow, Jr., first Black State Judge and State Senator; Collin Bennett, Black City Council member; Lewis Fox, local attorney and Board of Education member; George B. Kinsella, Hartford's mayor; Rev. Robert A. Moody, a Black Baptist minister and community activist; Robert Morris, Black Caucus spokesperson; and Wilber G. Smith, Black attorney, civil rights activist and, later, State Senator. Many other state and city officials are also present in the meeting images.
Related Materials
James Karales Photographs, 1953-2006 (photographs taken at civil rights marches)
Spider Martin Photographs, 1965, 1968 (photographs taken at civil rights marches)
SNCC Digital Gateway Project Files, 2002-2018 (bulk 2010-2018)
African American civil rights workers -- Photographs; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History -- 20th century; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Press coverage; African Americans and mass media -- United States; Civil rights movements -- Connecticut -- History -- 20th century -- Photographs; Mass media and race relations -- United States; Photojournalists -- Connecticut -- Hartford; Political activists -- Connecticut -- Hartford -- History -- Photographs; Student protesters -- Photographs; Hartford (Conn.) -- History; Hartford (Conn.) -- Photographs; Hartford (Conn.) -- Politics and government; Hartford (Conn.) -- Race relations; Connecticut -- Race relations; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; News photographs; John Hope Franklin Research Center for African and African American History and Culture; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Community Renewal Team of Greater Hartford (Conn.); Barber, John, circa 1936-; Bennett, Collin B., Rev., 1931-1998; Black Caucus (Hartford, Conn.); Fox, Lewis, 1904-1976; Kinsella, George B., 1927-2016; Moody, Robert A., 1895-; Barlow, Boce W., Jr., 1915-2005; Smith, Wilber, -1992
- Black Caucus press photographs
  Arrangement
  These fifty press photographs documenting the Fall 1967 Hartford, Connecticut Black Caucus protests and meetings are arranged in chronological order. Almost all titles and dates originating from notes or captions on the backs of the prints.
  - FOR THE RECORD - Officer Stephen Hankard tape records John Barber's conversation with Capt. Benjamin Goldstein, 1967 September 15; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0001)
    Scope and Contents
    Edition run notes and newsprint caption glued on verso. Title taken from caption. Date in pencil on verso.
  - Black Caucus, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0002)
    Edition run notes glued on verso. Slug for article is "Walk" - image is of group of Black Caucus members walking down the sidewalk at night. Title taken from caption. Date in pencil on verso.
  - ON THE LINE - Black Caucus spokesman makes a point during meeting with Mayor George Kinsella in Police Department Lobby, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0003)
    Caption continues, "Group, which included Negroes and whites, surrounds pair along with press and police. Session over, group heads up up Morgan Street towards Main Street and home." Edition run notes and newsprint caption glued on verso. Title taken from caption. Date in pencil on verso.
  - Robert Morris - Black Caucus spokesman, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0004)
    Date and title from print verso.
  - Black Caucus meeting, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0005)
  - No known title, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0006)
    Date from print verso. Another image from Black Caucus meeting.
  - No known title, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0007)
  - Black Caucus meeting, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0008)
  - Robert Morris (left) - Rev. Moody, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0009)
    Date and title from print verso. Another image from Black Caucus meeting.
  - Left-right - Attorney Howard Klebanoff - Arthur Johnson, executive director, Human Relations Commission - The Rev. Herbert Smith [?] - Alfred White, chairman of H.R.C., 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0010)
  - No known title, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0011)
    Editorial and crop marks on front of print in orange pencil. Date from print verso. Crowd shot from Black Caucus meeting.
  - Arthur Johnson - executive director - Human Relations Commission, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0012)
    Date and title from print verso. Black Caucus meeting.
  - Mayor George Kinsella, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0013)
  - Wilber Smith, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0014)
    Date and title from print verso. Black Caucus meeting. This is one of two duplicates in the folder.
  - Wilber Smith, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0015)
    Date and title from print verso. Black Caucus meeting. This is the second of two duplicates in the folder.
  - John J. Gale - AIM president - (American Independent Movement) - Hall High School teacher, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0016)
    Date and title from print verso. Black Caucus meeting. John J. Gale (1920-2001) was the Hartford chairman of AIM, a political organization that appears to be still active, currently based in San Diego.
  - Councilman Collin Bennett, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0017)
    Date and title from print verso. Black Caucus meeting. The Reverend Collin B. Bennett (1931-1998) was a native of Jamaica and came to Connecticut in 1951, where he became a realtor. He was elected to the city council in 1965. (Source: Hartford Public Library "Hartford Changemakers web page, accessed Jan. 28, 2021)
  - Bose Barlow, 1967 September 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0018)
    Date and title from print verso. Black Caucus meeting. Boce W. Barlow, Jr. (1915-2005) was Connecticut's first Black municipal court judge and first Black state senator. (Source: Hartford Public Library "Hartford Changemakers" web page, accessed Jan. 28, 2021)
  - Black Caucus press meeting - Auburn St, Hartford, 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0019)
    Title and date taken from print verso.
  - John Barber, Black Caucus, 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0020)
  - Black Caucus - CRT meeting [Community Renewal Team], 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0021)
  - Councilman Collin Bennett, 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0022)
    Date and title from print verso. CRT meeting. The Reverend Collin B. Bennett (1931-1998) was a native of Jamaica and came to Connecticut in 1951, where he became a realtor. He was elected to the city council in 1965. (Source: Hartford Public Library "Hartford Changemakers web page, accessed Jan. 28, 2021)
  - John J. Gale (left) - Lewis Fox, 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0023)
    Date and title from print verso. CRT meeting. John J. Gale was a member of the American Independent Movement and a teacher; Lewis Fox (d. 1976) was a lawyer and member of the Hartford Board of Education.
  - Black Caucus - CRT meeting [Community Renewal Team], 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0024)
    Title and date were taken from print verso.
  - Black Caucus - CRT meeting [Community Renewal Team], 1967 September 22; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0025)
  - Robert Morris (center) - John Barber (right) - Black Caucus, 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0026)
  - WHAT'S AHEAD - Black Caucus spokesmen outline plans for the future to the Community Renewal Team's task force., 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0027)
    Caption continues, "From left: James Brown, Francis Gamble, Robert Morris, and John Barber." Title taken from caption on print verso. Date in pencil on verso. Edition run notes and newsprint caption glued on verso. Editorial and crop marks on front of print in orange pencil. Slug for article noted as "John Barber."
  - Black Caucus, 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0028)
  - John Barber, Black Caucus, 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0029)
  - Black Caucus - CRT [Community Renewal Team] Task Force meeting, 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0030)
  - John Barber, Black Caucus, 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0031)
  - Thomas Bodine, Community Renewal Team, 1967 September 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0032)
    Date and title from print verso. Thomas Bodine (1915-2005) served as a Commissioner of the Hartford Housing Authority for over 20 years. He was Chairman of the Community Renewal Team, from 1967-1970. (Source: Hartford Courant obituary web page, accessed Jan. 28, 2021)
  - Black Caucus - Barry Square, 1967 September 29; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0033)
    Title taken from caption on print verso. Date in pencil on verso. Edition run notes and newsprint caption glued on verso. Later date stamp, October 4. Editorial and crop marks on front of print in orange pencil. Slug for article noted as "Crowd."
  - SOGGY RALLY - John Barber of Hartford's Black Caucus, wearing striped cap, addresses group at Constitution Plaza., 1967 September 29; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0034)
    Caption continues, "Rain held attendance down as Barber promised further demonstrations." Title taken from caption on print verso. Date is taken from earlier photograph from the same march. Edition run notes and newsprint caption glued on verso. Later date stamp, Sept. 30. Editorial marks on front of print in green. Slug for article noted as "Crowd." "Black Caucus" also pencilled on verso.
  - BLACK CAUCUS marchers led by John Barber are flanked by line of policemen, right, Friday night, 1967 September 29; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0035)
    Newsprint caption glued on verso. Title taken from caption. Date is taken from earlier photograph from the same march. Later date stamp, Sept. 30. "Black Caucus - March to South End of Hartford" and "Main St and Pratt [?]" also pencilled on verso.
  - No known title, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0036)
    Large group of protesters, photographed from above, in the Hall of Flags, Hartford State Capitol Building. Date appears in pencil on print verso.
  - No known title, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0037)
    Group of protesters walk down the sidewalk next to a parking lot. Date appears in pencil on print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 12.
  - John F. Merchant - State Deputy Community Affairs Commission, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0038)
    Location is unknown, but may be State Capitol. Title and date taken from print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 12.
  - John F. Merchant - State Deputy Community Affairs Commission, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0039)
    Meeting room location is unknown, but may be State Capitol. Title and date taken from print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 12.
  - John F. Merchant - State Deputy Community Affairs Commission, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0040)
  - No known title, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0041)
    Group of protesters in Capitol Building looking at the replica Liberty Bell. Date appears in pencil on print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 12.
  - No known title, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0042)
    Group of protesters in Capitol Building, photographed from above, looking at the replica Liberty Bell. Date appears in pencil on print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 12.
  - No known title, 1967 October 6; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0043)
    Protesters, photographed from above, in the Rotunda Hall, Hartford State Capitol Building, looking at statue of Nathan Hale. Date appears in pencil on print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 12.
  - John Barber addressing Bushnell Park college group, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0044)
  - John Barber, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0045)
    Title and date taken from print verso. Another image from the Bushnell Park gathering.
  - John Barber, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0046)
  - No known title, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0047)
  - No known title, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 1/2 x 8 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0048)
    Title and date taken from print verso. Two White young adults hold up sign saying "We support Black Caucus."
  - March to Bushnell Park, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0049)
  - MARCHERS escorted by police file quietly through West Hartford during Black Caucus demonstration Friday night, 1967 October 12; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 1/2 x 6 1/2 inches. (Box 1, Print RL.11878-P-0050)
    Newsprint caption glued on verso. Title taken from caption; date from note on print verso. Later date stamp, Oct. 14. "Black Caucus" also pencilled on verso. Single editorial mark on front. The actual date for Friday night, mentioned in the caption, would have been Oct. 13; thus this may be a different protest than that at Bushnell Park, one night earlier on Oct. 12 according to dates on the prints.